I know you guys don't want to do this, but we have no choice.
Je sais très bien que vous n'avez pas envie de le faire.
You can either bitch and whine or we can get it over with.
Soit vous râle: et pleurnichez, soit on s'en débarrasse.
-I got whine. -I got the B-word.
- Je pleurniche. - Je râle.
Yeah, well, it's in our contract to serve on a university committee.
Ce contrat nous oblige à participer à un comité universitaire.
And frankly, this is one I believe in, okay? Here:
Et c‘est une cause a laquelle je crois:
Encouraging more women to pursue a career in the sciences.
encourager les femmes a devenir des scientifiques.
Come on, if I was good at convincing women to do stuff...
Si je savais convaincre les femmes,
...I wouldn't have spent so much of my 20's in the shower. Heh.
je n'aurais pas passé majeunesse sous la douche.
If you ask me, this whole thing is a waste of our time.
Si tu veux mon avis, on perd notre temps.
-Helping women? -Yeah, helping anyone.
- A aider les femmes ? - A aider qui que ce soit.
People should take care of themselves.
Les gens doivent se prendre en charge.
Oh, like yesterday when you made me drive you to the dry cleaners...
Comme hier, quand j'ai dû t'amener au pressing,
...the pharmacy and the post office?
àla pharmacie et a la poste ?
I'm not saying people can't use tools.
On peut utiliser des instruments.
Even an otter picks up a rock when he wants a clam.
La loutre prend bien une pierre pour ouvrir un coquillage.
You don't think it's worthwhile to get more women in science?
Tu ne crois pas qu'il faut plus de femmes en sciences ?
I think that's incredibly sexist of you.
Je crois que c‘est extrèmement sexiste.
I believe in a gender-blind society like in Star Trek...
Je crois en une société sans discrimination, comme Star Trek,
...where women and men of all races and creeds work side by side as equals.
où hommes et femmes de toutes races travaillent ensemble, égaux.
You mean where they were advanced enough to invent an interstellar warp drive...
Tu veux dire où ils sont assez avancés
...but a black lady still answered the space phone?
mais une femme noire répond encore au téléphone de l'espace ?
Oh, I did spend a lot of my shower time with Lieutenant Uhura.
J'en ai passé du temps sous la douche avec le lieutenant Uhura.
Howard's disturbing recollections aside...
Les souvenirs troublants d'Howard mis a part,
...I don't appreciate being forced to do banal committee work.
je n'aime pas qu'on m'oblige à travailler pour un comité.
I know. You're too smart for this.
Tu es trop intelligent pour ça.
Exactly. It's like asking the Human Torch to heat up your frozen burrito.
Oui. C‘est comme demander àla Torche humaine
Got it. All right, I'm thinking one way to counter bias in the peer-review process...
Pour contrecarrer les préjugés dans les évaluations
...is for papers to be submitted under gender-neutral names...
on pourrait utiliser l'initiale plutôt que le prénom en entier.
...like S. Smith instead of Samantha Smith.
comme S. Smith pour Samantha Smith.
I suppose there is a history of professional women...
Des femmes ont utilisé leurs initiales pour éviter les préjugés :
Harry Potter's J.K. Rowling, uh, Star Trek's D.C. Fontana.
J.K. Rowling pour Harry Potter, D.C. Fontana pour Star Trek.
Van Nuys pole-dancer, D.D. Melons.
D.D. Melons, Ia strip—teaseuse de Van Nuys.
All right. I think we've really helped women today. Let's fire up the Xbox.
Super. On a bien aidé les femmes. Faisons chauffer la Xbox.
Don't make this a school project where I'm the smart kid doing the work...
On se croirait a l‘école où l‘élève doué fait tout le boulot,
...while the slackers sit and watch.
et les tire-au-flanc Ie regardent.
We're not. You're the smart kid doing all the work...
Non. Tu es l‘élève doué qui fait tout le boulot,
...while the even smarter kids sit back and watch.
pendant que les encore plus doués regardent.
So you think I'm one of the smarter kids?
Alors je suis un des élèves doués ?
No, you're a tool I was using to make my point.
Tu es un instrument nécessaire a ma démonstration.
Guys, our topic is "Encouraging Women in Science."
On veut encourager les femmes a faire des sciences.
Can you at least play a less sexist game?
Choisissez un jeu moins sexiste.
How is it sexist?
En quoi est-il sexiste ?
My character wields a battle ax as well as any man.
Mon personnage manie la hache aussi bien qu'un homme.
Not to mention she has mammary glands that could nurse a family of 30.
Et elle a des seins qui nourrirait une famille de 30.
And have enough milk left over to open a Baskin-Robbins.
Et il lui resterait assez de lait pour ouvrir une crémerie.
Mother, warrior-princess, franchise owner...
Mère, princesse-guerrière, propriétaire de magasin,
...I hear glass ceilings shattering all over town.
ton personnage est une inspiration pour toutes les femmes.
Sheldon, you're always saying how much smarter you are than me.
Sheldon, tu passes ton temps a dire que tu es plus intelligent que moi.
Spend five seconds and come up with one idea on how to get more women into science.
Donne—moi juste une idée pour recruter plus de femmes.
All your ideas address the issue at a university level. By then it's too late.
Tu abordes le problème au niveau de l‘université.
You need to design a program that targets girls at the middle-school level...
Tu dois faire un programme qui s‘adresse aux filles en collège
...and sets them on an academic track towards the hard sciences.
pour les aiguiller vers les sciences.
That's actually good. Why didn't I think of that?
Bonne idée. Pourquoi n'y ai-je pas pensé ?
Some people are otters, some people are rocks.
Il y a les loutres, et puis il y a les pierres.
I wonder if there's a way we could give the idea a trial run.
Je me demande si on pourrait tester notre idée.
I could call my old middle school, see if we can talk to some of the female students.
Je pourrais appeler mon collège,
Great. Try to set up something for us to go over there.
Super. Essaie d‘organiser ça.
Hold on. While I'm comfortable speaking about science...
Attends. Parler sciences n‘est pas un problème,
...l'm not sure I know how to spark the interest of school children. Better Google it.
mais je ne suis pas sûr de savoir éveiller l‘intérêt de collégiennes.
What exactly are you looking up?
Qu'est—ce que tu cherches ?
"How do I get 12-year-old girls excited?"
"Comment exciter des filles de 12 ans ?"
Thanks again for letting me crash girl's night.
Merci de m‘avoir laissé gâcher votre soirée filles.
Are you kidding? You brought fancy wine and made fondue.
Tu plaisantes ?
I've slept with guys for less.
J'ai couché pour moins que ça.
It's ajoke.
C‘est une blague.
Based on real events.
Basées sur des faits réels.
Anyway, I was hoping I could, uh, pick your brains a little.
J'espérais que vous pourriez m'aider.
I'm supposed to take Lucy out Friday and I need a killer first date.
Je dois sortir avec Lucy vendredi, etj'ai besoin d‘une idée géniale.
Evolutionary biology says that women are attracted to a man...
D'après la biologie évolutionnaire, la femme est attirée
...who is steady in the face of danger, sol recommend an unsafe environment.
par l‘homme qui n‘a pas peur du danger,
A seedy bar on the wrong side of the tracks...
Un bar sordide dans un quartier louche,
...a picnic near a lunatic asylum...
un pique—nique près d'un asile de fous,
...a wine-tasting on skid row.
une dégustation de vin dans la zone.
Lucy has some, uh, social anxiety issues, we could start with something simpler.
Lucy a des problèmes en public,
Why don't you take her to Disneyland?
Améne-la à Disneyland.
You go on Space Mountain, you're in the dark, she's holding onto you.
Space Mountain, vous êtes dans le noir, elle s'accroche à toi.
That ride is shorter than you think...
Oui, mais c‘est plus court qu'on pense,
...and they take a picture of you at the end, so make sure you got your clothes on.
et ils prennent une photo àla fin,
It's ajoke.
C‘est une blague.
Based on real events.
Basée sur des faits réels.
Disneyland? I don't know.
Disneyland ? Je ne sais pas.
With all the crowds and the weird characters walking around...
Avec la foule et tous ces personnages bizarres,
...just reminds me too much of India.
j'ai l'impression d'être en Inde.
I haven't been since I was a kid. We should go one weekend.
Ça remonte à loin pour moi. On devrait y aller un week-end.
Weekends are too crowded.
C‘est bondé le week-end.
-So blow off work, go on a weekday. -Hooky?
Dis que tu es malade. Vas—y en semaine.
I've never played hooky in my life.
Je n'ai jamais séché les cours.
My mom said that's how girls end up addicted to reefer and jazz music.
D‘après ma mère, c‘est comme ça
More like how girls end up at a Best Western hotel...
C'était plutôt finir dans un hôtel Ibis
...with a 34-year-old guy named Luther.
avec un type de 34 ans, qui s'appelait Luther.
-Joke? -I can laugh about it now.
- Encore une blague ? - Je peux en rire maintenant.
What do you say? This Friday we ditch work and go to Disneyland?
Alors, vendredi, on sèche le boulot et on va à Disneyland ?
-l'm in. -Me too.
- Je suis partante. - Moi aussi.
Excuse me, I thought we were trying to solve my problem.
Pardon. Je croyais qu'on essayait de résoudre mon problème.
Oh, yeah, right.
Ah, oui.
Wait, what was your problem again?
C'était quoi ton problème déjà ?
I'm a man who can't talk to women, trying to figure out how to go on a romantic date...
Je suis un homme timide avec les femmes,
...with a girl who suffers from social anxiety, she can't be around other people.
pour sortir avec une fille qui souffre de phobie sociale.
Yeah, that's a toughie.
Ouais, c‘est pas gagné.
Let's think.
Voyons.
Are we doing just Disney or California Adventure too?
On vajuste à Disney, ou aussi a California Adventure ?
It's nice of your old school to let us try out our science talk on some female students.
C‘est sympa qu‘ils nous laissent tester
They were actually pretty excited. I'm their most famous alum.
Ils étaient ravis. Je suis leur ancien élève le plus célèbre.
If you don't count the serial killer who ate all those prostitutes.
Après le tueur en série qui a mangé toutes ces prostituées.
This must feel good for you, coming back to your alma mater as an astronaut.
Ça doit être cool de revenir dans son collège en tant qu‘astronaute.
Yeah. Last time I was here I was just a scrawny little nerd.
La dernière fois que j‘étais ici, j‘étais un maigrichon coincé.
And now you're also an astronaut.
Et maintenant, tu es aussi astronaute.
So many memories. How many times in these hallways...
Que de souvenirs. Combien de fois dans ces couloirs,
...was I tripped, punched and spit on? Heh.
on m‘a fait des croche-pieds, frappé et craché dessus ?
Oh, look, here's my old locker.
Regardez, mon ancien casier.
l have a masters in engineering...
Je suis ingénieur, etje n'arrive toujours pas a comprendre
-Hey. -What?
- Hé. - Quoi ?
Nothing.
Rien.
Smart, we don't want any problems.
Bien vu, on ne veut pas d‘histoire.
I can't believe I ditched work for Disneyland.
C‘est fou, je sèche le boulot.
What did you tell your boss?
- Qu'as-tu dit a ton chef ? - J'ai assuré, j'ai fait par étapes.
At 7 last night I called about a problem at the lab...
Je l'ai appelé hier a 19 h pour un problème au labo
...and casually mentioned I was going out for seafood.
etj'ai glissé que j'allais manger des fruits de mer.
At 9:30, I called and told him that one of my scallops tasted weird.
A 21h30, je l'ai appelé pour lui dire
At 11:30, I called and said I was throwing up like a fire hose.
A 23h30, j'ai appelé pour dire que je vomissais mes tripes.
At 12:45, I called and made nothing but dry-heaving sounds.
A 00h45, j'ai appelé etje n'ai émis que des gémissements.
And now I'm going to Disneyland!
Et maintenantje vais à Disneyland !
Penny, what did you say?
Penny, tu as dit quoi ?
I work at the Cheesecake Factory. I said, "Bye."
Je travaille dans un restaurant, je suis juste partie.
So, what are we gonna do first?
On commence par quoi ?
I don't know about you, but I'm going to the place that gives you a princess makeover.
Je ne sais pas vous,
Ooh, that sounds like fun.
Ça a l‘air sympa.
You're kidding, right? We're notjust gonna get drunk and go on rides?
Vous rigolez ? On ne va pas se soûler
Come on, do it with us.
Allez, fais-Ie avec nous.
Ah, all right, whatever. How does it work?
D‘accord. Ça marche comment ?
Okay, so you pick your princess, Sleeping Beauty, Snow White, Cinderella.
Tu choisis La belle au bois dormant, Blanche—Neige ou Cendrillon.
They give you hair, makeup, the works.
On te donne le costume et du maquillage.
I guess it would be fun to be Cinderella.
Oui, ce sera cool d'étre Cendrillon.
-I want to be Cinderella too. -Yeah.
- Je veux aussi être Cendrillon. - Oui.
We can't all be Cinderella.
On ne peut pas toutes être Cendrillon.
Then how do we decide?
Comment on décide ?
Well, it's simple. This was my idea, I'm driving, I'm Cinderella.
C‘est facile. C‘était mon idée.
You bitches got a problem with that, we can stop the car right now.
Si vous avez un problème, on peut s‘arrêter ici.
Excuse me.
Pardon.
I'm meeting a girl here. It's kind of a first date.
J‘attends une fille. C‘est un rendez-vous amoureux.
In a library?
Dans une bibliothèque ?
She and l are both a little awkward in social situations so this seemed like a good idea.
On n‘est pas très à l'aise en public, alors ça me semblait une bonne idée.
May I join you?
Je peux me joindre à vous ?
No, you can'tjoin us.
Jamais dela vie.
Go climb back up whatever beanstalk you came down from.
Retournez dans le monde d'où vous venez.
You can do better.
Vous méritez mieux.
Oh, we're eating here?
On mange ici ?
We're having a texting date?
C‘est un rendez-vous par SMS ?
LUCY: [love that.
ça me plaît.
RAJESH: As you're reading, it will help to rememberlhave an adorable accent.
Pendant que tu lis,
Okay, who's ready for some science?
D‘accord, vous êtes prêtes à faire des sciences ?
Okay, I am Dr. Leonard Hofstadter.
Je suis Leonard Hofstadter.
I'm here with my friends, Dr. Cooper, and real-life astronaut Howard Wolowitz.
Je suis ici avec mes amis, M. Cooper
And we are going to show you girls how cool ajob in science can be.
On va vous montrer
How cool, you ask?
Super comment ?
Well, how about negative 273 degrees...
Que diriez-vous de 1 224 kmlh,
...because that's the temperature at which entropy reaches its minimum value.
car c‘est la Vitesse supersonique.
Did ljust learn something new and have fun doing it? What?
J'ai appris un truc nouveau etje m‘amuse en même temps!
So now let's bring out theoretical physicist, Dr. Sheldon Cooper!
C‘est au tour du docteur en physique théorique, Sheldon Cooper!
Hello, female children.
Bonjour, enfants filles.
Allow me to inspire you...
Permettez-moi de vous motiver
...with a story about a great female scientist.
avec l'histoire d‘une grande scientifique.
Polish-born, French-educated...
La Polonaise de naissance, éduquée en France,
...Madame Curie.
madame Curie.
Co-discoverer of radioactivity...
Co-découvreuse de la radioactivité,
...she was a hero of science. Until her hair fell out...
elle était une héroïne dela science. Jusqu‘à ce que ses cheveux tombent,
...her vomit and stool became filled with blood...
que son vomi et ses selles se teintent de sang,
...and she was poisoned to death by her own discovery.
et qu'elle meure, empoisonnée par sa propre découverte.
With a little hard work...
Avec un peu de travail,
...I see no reason why that can't happen to any of you.
je ne vois pas pourquoi ça ne pourrait pas vous arriver.
Are we done? Can we go?
On a fini ? On peut y aller ?
The thing to remember is you can go to outer space too.
Et n‘oubliez pas que vous aussi vous pouvez aller dans l‘espace.
Heh. I mean, look at me.
Regardez-moi.
I went to this very school. Those desks you're sitting in?
J‘étais dans ce collège.
l was once superglued to one of them.
On a tapissé la mienne de Super Glue.
Did you go to the moon?
Vous êtes allé sur la lune ?
No, but I did go to the International Space Station.
Non, mais je suis allé dans la Station spatiale internationale.
Did you fly the rocket?
Vous étiez le pilote ?
No, but I was in the rocket.
Non, mais j‘étais dans la fusée.
-I didn't actually-- -So you just flew around?
Alors vous ne faites que voler ?
That's kind of like my uncle. A flight attendant.
Comme mon oncle. Il est steward.
No, heh, I'm an American hero, your uncle brings people nuts, okay?
Non, je suis un héros américain. Ton oncle sert des cacahuètes.
All right, all right, all right.
C‘est bon.
Boy, we are learning a lot here, huh? Thank you, Astronaut Howard.
Qu'apprend-t-on comme trucs. Merci, astronaute Howard.
Um, I am what's called an experimental physicist.
Je suis un physicien expérimental.
Which is super fun because I get to test theories and work with lasers.
C‘est super cool, car je teste des théories etje me sers de laser.
-Yes? -How did you decide to become a scientist?
Pourquoi êtes-vous devenu un scientifique ?
Oh, excellent question.
Excellente question.
My mother and father are scientists, so I was kind of led in that direction.
Mes parents étaient des scientifiques,
Pushed might be a better way to describe it.
Poussé serait plus juste.
To be honest with you guys, when l was your age, I wanted to be a rap star.
Pour être honnête, a votre âge, je voulais être une star du rap.
Like Snoop Dogg, but with a healthy respect for the police.
Comme Snoop Dogg, mais avec du respect pour la police.
Yeah, no, sure, you laugh.
Bien sûr, ça vous fait rire.
Just like my mother did.
Comme ma mère.
[RAPPING] Afterl conï¬ded, I was derided and chided
Après m‘être conﬁé, ils m‘ont raillé et réprimandé
She said my dreams were misguided
Ma mère énervée m‘a dit que je rêvais
That's just a little freestyle.
C‘était un petit freestyle.
RAJESH: My dad's a gynecologist in India.
Mon père est gynécologue en Inde.
So if you're ever over there and need a checkup...
Si tu y vas et que tu as besoin d‘un check—up,
...as he likes to say, he's "at your cervix."
comme il dit : “Je suis ovaire. "
LUCY: That's terrible. Your dad should be sent to the pun-itentiary.
C‘est terrible. On devrait l‘envoyer au pénis-tentier.
RAJ ES H : That's a ï¬ning pun-ishment.
Oui, il ferait pénis-tence.
I still don't know what you do for a living.
Je ne sais toujours pas quel est ton travail.
L U CY : Web design.
Je fais des sites web.
RAJ ESH: Anything I might've seen?
J‘ai pu en voir ?
LUCY: I don't know. You ever look at porn websites?
Je ne sais pas. Tu as déjà été sur des sites de porno ?
RAJESH: No. Never. What is porn?
Non. Jamais. C‘est quoi le porno ?
LUCY: Sorry, auto-correct.
Pardon, je rectiﬁe.
That was supposed to say "prom websites. "
Je voulais dire des “sites de prom ".
RAJ ESH: Ooh, fun. Ilove prom.
Super, j‘adore.
The romance, the gowns, it's like a fairy tale come to life.
Les idylles, les robes, c‘est comme un conte de fées.
Sorry, auto-correct.
Pardon, je rectiﬁe.
That was supposed to say "I like sports."
Je voulais dire : “J‘adore le sport. "
I never wanted to play the cello.
Je ne voulais pas jouer du violoncelle.
How do you meet girls playing the cello?
Comment on rencontre des filles avec ça ?
"Hey, wanna come over to my house and hear me play an instrument...
"Tu veux venir chez moi et m'écouterjouer d'un instrument
...that sounds like a suicidal bumblebee?"
qui fait le bruit d‘une abeille suicidaire ?"
Quick, pull the fire alarm, let's get out of here.
Vite, va déclencher l'alarme incendie. Tirons-nous d'ici.
Uh, hello again. Um....
Re-bonjour.
Yeah, I don't know if women in general...
Je ne sais pas si en général,
...have been actively discouraged from pursuing the sciences...
les femmes ont été sciemment découragées de faire des sciences,
...but it's clear you young women here today have been.
mais ce qui est sûr, c‘est qu'aujourd'hui, vous l'avez été.
While I was listening to my colleagues waste your time...
J'écoutais mes collègues vous faire perdre votre temps,
...it occurred to me that it might be much more meaningful...
etje me suis dit que ce serait plus intéressant pour vous,
...to hear about women in science from actual women in science.
d'entendre parler des femmes scientifiques
And, uh, I happen to know two brilliant examples...
Etj'en connais deux brillants exemples,
...who have agreed to speak to you on the phone right now.
qui ont accepté de vous parler au téléphone.
Uh, Dr. Rostenkowski, Dr. Fowler? Are you there?
Mlle Rostenkowski, Mlle Fowler ? Vous êtes la ?
AMY [OVER PHONE]: We're here.
Nous sommes la.
Thank you for taking time out of your busy schedule to enlighten these young women.
Merci de prendre le temps d'éclairer ces jeunes filles,
It's our pleasure.
Avec plaisir.
I'm Dr. Fowler, and I'm a neuroscientist.
Je suis Mlle Fowler, docteur en neurosciences.
And I'm Dr. Rostenkowski-Wolowitz, and I'm a microbiologist.
Etje suis Mme Rostenkowski-Wolowitz,
The world of science needs more women, but from a young age...
Le monde des sciences a besoin de plus de femmes, mais très tôt,
...we girls are encouraged to care more about the way we look...
on nous encourage à nous préoccuper
...than about the power of our minds.
que de nos capacités intellectuelles.
That's true. Every one of you has the capacity to be anything you want to be.
C‘est vrai. Chacune de vous a les capacités de faire ce qu'elle veut.
Unless you wanna be Cinderella.
Sauf si elle veut être Cendrillon.
Come at me, see what happens.
Tu me cherches ?
RAJ ES H : This was really fun.
C‘était très sympa,
My battery's dying, so I'm just gonna talk.
Ma batterie est déchargée, alors je vais parler.
Thanks for today.
Merci pour aujourd'hui.
I've been trying to do more things that scare me.
J'essaie de faire plus de choses qui m'effraient.
And coming here was definitely one of them.
Et venir ici était l‘une d'elles.
But it was also really nice.
Mais c‘était aussi trés agréable.
So thanks, and, um, I'm gonna go.
Alors merci, etje vais y aller.
Maybe I could do one more scary thing before I go and give you a kiss goodbye?
Peut-être que je peux faire une autre chose effrayante et t'embrasser ?
You know, if that's okay.
Si tu veux bien.
Panic attack! Maybe next time.
Crise de panique ! La prochaine fois.
I'm counting that as foreplay.
Je compte ça comme un préliminaire.
Bernie, I'm home.
Bernie, je suis rentré.
You have fun today?
Tu t‘es amusée ?
BERNADETTE: Yes. And I have a surprise for you.
Oui, etj'ai une surprise pour toi.
Please be Cinderella, please be Cinderella.
S'il te plaît, sois Cendrillon.
Well, hello, Prince Charming.
Salut, prince charmant.
Milady.
Madame.
Hey, how was your--? What?
Hé, comment était... Quoi ?
I can explain. I played hooky with the girls and we all went to Disneyland and go--
On a séché le boulot avec les filles, et on est allées à Disneyland...
-What are you doing? -Disneyland, go on, I'm listening.
- Qu'est—ce que tu fais ? - Disneyland, continue, je t'écoute.
All Snow White needs is one little kiss to wake up.
Tout ce dont a besoin Blanche-Neige, c‘est d'un baiser pour se réveiller.
Heard you the first time.
Je t‘ai entendue la première fois.
[English - us - an]
[French]